Okay, hello, and welcome to our third lecture on the limits of
knowledge hypothesis significance testing. So, in the past few
lectures, you've probably, at least had some reason to think
about what the problems are with null hypothesis significance
testing, so not just the problems due to incorrect use of null
hypothesis significance testing, although those are definitely
there and definitely an issue, but also the general issues with
null hypothesis significance testing, with this particular
method of trying to get evidence for a particular hypothesis.
Okay, so we've already mentioned in the previous lecture, type
one error and type two error. So type one error is when you
reject the null hypothesis, even though it is true, and the
probability of that is called alpha. A type two error is when
you fail to reject the null hypothesis even though it is false.
And the alternative hypothesis which is here called H1 is true.
And the probability of making this error is called beta. Now, of
course, if not, if this is true, and we are not rejecting it,
then that is a correct decision. And if you have looked at the
some of the problems in the seminar activity for last week, then
you might also see that this, the probability of making this
correct decision is for diagnostic test is called specificity.
Okay. And then finally, the other correct decision that you can
make is to reject the null hypothesis. If it is actually false,
and the alternative hypothesis is true. The probability of doing
this is called power, and then a diagnostic test. This would be
known as sensitivity. Okay, so we want to avoid a type one
error. Right? So how do you control it? Well, first of all, we
control the type one error rate directly because of the way no
hypothesis significance testing works, by just setting alpha to
an appropriate level. And usually we're using .05, right. But
there are many factors that can increase the type one error
rate, and we saw one in our first workshop question for last
week, if you remember, we talked about if we have my many tests,
and each individual test has a type one error rate on alpha
level of .05, how do these individual alphas add up to the whole
family, or in the whole family of tests. And that is, for
example, a problem when you do neuroscience. And when you
analyse brain areas, and you want to compare lots of activation
and lots of different brain areas, and you are ready to reject
your null hypothesis that maybe is just nothing changes in the
brain, I don't really care about which area, I just care at my
normal processes, it's just I can see I will not see the effect
anywhere. And then I have 40 different areas. And I do 40
different t-tests on brain activation in those areas. So in this
case, I definitely have to control the error, or control the
alpha, because so you did this in the workshop for for 40
comparisons, right. And you remember it was about the
probability was about 87%, of making at least one type one error
in the 40 tests. The more tests you make, of course, the closer
the probability gets to 100. And that is just, if I have a test
that has a 5% probability built in of making an error, then the
more often I do the test, the more often I'm going to get the
error. So even if, if for a single test, right down here, it's
quite low. Even for two tests, that's already above .05, right.
And if I make many tests, I mean, even if I do -- if I have just
20 tests -- we already have a Type I error rate of about 60%
Alright, so you need to control for this. Otherwise, you're
going to make a mistake. If what you're doing is, you have one,
no hypothesis that you would reject. Given any significant
result of any of these tests, it's important to keep in mind if
you if you have two different hypotheses, and you do two t
tests, and each one tests a completely different hypothesis. And
t test number two does not affect hypothesis number one, then
you don't have a test family, and then you don't have to correct
right, it is about rejecting one null hypothesis, but you have
multiple ways of rejecting it, because you're doing multiple
comparisons. Okay. So this is called the family-wise Type I
error rate. And as I just said, a family of hypothesis tests is
a number of tests that would each on their own, lead you to
reject one single null hypothesis. So for example, let's say
you're testing the intervention on depression, and you want to
see if the treatment group differs from the control group in
terms of mood, activity, and sleep quality. So you're measuring
these three dependent variables for each of the sort of the
difference in these variables for each of the four, the control
group and the treatment group. And you conduct one t-test each
for for each of these measures. So your hypothesis is just that
the intervention has an effect, you don't care about whether the
effect is on mood, activity, sleep quality, a combination of two
of them, all three of them, you're happy, if it makes any
difference at all, okay, in this case, those three tests form a
test family, because you will reject the overall hypothesis that
says my treatment has no effect. If any of those three t tests
become significant, and then you can just calculate what would
the family-wise Type I error rate be? In this scenario, so you
have three tests with an alpha of 5%, of .05, and you're going
to reject the overall hypothesis, no matter which one of those
tests reaches significance, or maybe two, or maybe three, could
could be any of those cases. And, as we've talked about, in the
workshop last week, and as we talked about in the previous
slide, this probability is 1 - .95 cubed, so to the third power,
and that gives us .143. So 14.3% probability of rejecting the
null hypothesis, even if it is true. So even if there is
absolutely no true difference, in any of these three variables,
we have a 14% probability of rejecting the null hypothesis and
committing a type one error. Okay, and that is no longer that is
no longer our 5% a
lpha. Right? So if we said, oh, yeah, 5% probability of, of
incorrectly rejecting the null hypothesis I'm okay with with
that, right. But now we have a 14.3% probability of incorrectly
rejecting the null hypothesis. So what can we do about this. And
the easiest way to controlling the familywize type one error
rate, but also the most radical way, is the Bonferroni
correction. And if you've done undergraduate statistics, you
have heard of that.
What you do for the Bonferroni correction is you simply use a
different alpha. So you lower the alpha level by dividing it by
the number of tests. And you can see that it works. So if we in
this case, we use an alpha of .05 divided by three. So .05 is
our overall overall family wide alpha. And now for each
individual test, we then use an alpha of .017. Now, of course,
that makes it harder for us to reject our null hypothesis. So it
lowers our power, it increases the probability of a Type II
error. But in general, in null hypothesis significance testing
we feel that a Type I error is worse than a Type II error. So
what we will try to do first is control the type one error and
then see what the consequences of this are for a Type II error.
So if we look at what this does to our type one error rate, so
now we have, instead of .95, we now have .983, some, so 1 -
.017, which is our new corrected alpha, right? So we cube that.
And so we get .049. So it's a little bit lower, even then our
original alpha of .05, but it's close enough. Because it is
mathematically so easy that we can, we are fine with doing it
backwards. So although, of course, for every little bit that you
move the that you lower the alpha, you increase the beta, so the
probability of making a Type II error, and you lower your power.
So but the main thing is that with this correction, our Type I
error rate is just below .05, just like we wanted. Okay, there
are variations of this correction. So that's the Bonferroni home
correction, for example, where you say, Okay, I don't correct
all the tests equally, but rather, I have, if I have one test
that I particularly care about, then I can correct that one
less, and the other ones more, and I still get the overall Type
I error rate that I'm interested in. But basically, the basic
principle is the same, you sacrifice some power in order to keep
the Type I error rate controlled. And the Bonferroni-Holm
method, as opposed to the standard Bonferroni method, just helps
you do this. So you get the maximum possible power for the one
comparison, maybe you care most about. Okay. So that's multiple
comparisons. And and you need to be honest about what a multiple
or multiple comparison is. Because often people are not honest
about what tests are a family. But, for example, if you're
testing eight variables, and so maybe you might be, you might be
telling yourself, yeah, I wouldn't, I wouldn't report this as
significant. If just, if it just comes out in one of the
variables, it has to come out in two or something like that. Is
that really what you're going to do? It is it is a good idea to
actually write down your decision strategy, and then stick to
it. And we'll we'll be talking about pre-registration, a little
bit in Lecture five. But that is part of the idea is, is that
you that you stick to one decision criterion, so you can't just
move go moving the goalposts because you say, "Oh, I thought I
was going to find an effect on mood. But I also tested sleep
quality. And sleep quality is of course, a completely different
hypothesis. So now, I'm going to report --- So I'm going to say,
oh, yeah, this is significant. I'm going to just pretend that I
was interested in sleep quality to begin with." That doesn't
work; that is moving the goalposts. Okay. Multiple comparisons
are not the only way to increase the type one error rate. So in
the lecture last week, I showed you an example of an optional
stopping rule. And these stopping rules the way they work is --
and this is something that people used to do all the time. And
in actual research, because they didn't know any better. They
thought this was fine.
So if you so let's say you have collected 30 participants, and
you just look and see what what the data look like. Because it's
in general a good idea to check what you're actually doing, what
data you're actually collecting. It's good to check on the data
quality. Sure. And just to make sure that everything works, you
run the significance test and you find, yeah, I have a
significant effect. So great. So you stop data collection, and
you decide to publish the results with a significant effect. Now
the problem is, if you don't get a significant result, what do
you do then? Maybe, and this used to be very, very common, that
when people went to talk to their dissertation supervisors, the
supervisor would say, "Oh yeah, you didn't get any results after
30 participants, oh, well run 10 more people see what happens."
And that is an optional stopping rule. Because that means if I
had gotten a significant result after 30, participant, I would
have stopped here. Now I'm running 40 participants. So now after
40 participants, if I now have a significant result, then I can
stop. But if I still don't have one, maybe I'll run 10 more,
maybe I'll go to 50 participants. But you see that each of these
tests, each of these tests is is a new comparison. I mean, is
the the thing that makes people feel better about this is that
they're not, of course, not completely independent from each
other, because you still have the 30 participants from the first
test. But you have to treat this, essentially, as a new test
that you are performing. And that new test. Well, at worst has
another .05 alpha. Right. So now, with the optional stuffing
rule, you're again, performing essentially multiple comparisons,
and you're just picking and choosing the one that is
significant, right? Maybe when you have a significant effect,
after 30, then you collect data from some participants who don't
show the effect. So maybe you just had, maybe you just had good
luck or bad luck to get a couple of participants where the
effect is randomly strong. And then you get, and then the next
10, it's not going to be very strong. So after 40 participants,
maybe you wouldn't get the effect significant anymore. But if
you have stopped collecting the data after 30, because you found
a significant result, you would never get to these other
participants, right? So you need to have a firm stopping rule.
You can say, I'm going to stop after 40 participant data sets,
no matter what happens, then you are fine, because then you
perform one test. And and that's the test that that counts. And
then if you have this firm stopping rule, of course, you could
peek at the data and say, "Oh, yeah, if I had stopped collecting
data now, the effect would be significant. But oh, well, I need
to see what happens after 40 participants, I can't just stop at
30, just because the effect is significant." You have to be
principled like that. And a lot of people aren't, and a lot of
people don't realise that it's a big deal, which is why this is
so important. And especially if the test narrowly missed
significance. So I told you last week, a p value of .07 is for
the purposes of null hypothesis significance testing is
absolutely no different from a p value of .99, right, it is not
significant. It is not marginal, it is not almost significant.
It is it is simply not significant. But of course, people like
just like when you are when you miss the train by 10 seconds
instead of by 10 minutes. Where the end result is the same.
You're not on the train, right. But
people find it is much more frustrating to miss the train by 10
seconds, then by 10 minutes, because it's much easier to imagine
how it could have worked. So that is that is one of the biases
that Daniel Kahneman studied, right. So, of course, and of
course, psychology researchers are as vulnerable to these biases
as everyone else. So people say, Oh, well, I have .07 that is so
close to significant. So if I just run five more participants,
then I'll probably get insignificant. And maybe it'll happen.
Right? The problem is that you would have to collect to correct
for making this decision to collect five more participants. And
that is correcting for it is quite tricky. I mean, in the worst
case, you would have to have your alpha, right, because you're
doing two tests, two comparisons now. And then of course, a
p-value, even if after five more participants, you get a p-value
of .05, that's no longer going to be significant. So But people
imagine that they don't have to correct for this. And then, even
worse, let's say it gets the effect gets a tiny bit stronger
after five more participants, but it's still not at the
criterion. So P equals .06 we're moving in the right direction,
let's just get some more participants. And I think what
underlies this problem is that people correctly feel that a
p-value --- So a result that leads to a p-value of .06 is not
that different from a result that leads to a p value of .049.
But if you're doing no hypothesis significance testing, it
completely changes your decision. And that is just because you
put the criterion there, you have to put your criterion
somewhere. Otherwise, you can't use not hypothesis significance
testing, you have to have your criterion to reject or not
reject. Right? And because people naturally see, well, these
results are not that different. I could easily get from non
significant to significant event, just add a few participants.
The problem is that then the whole test strategy for for null
hypothesis significance testing, but the whole idea that we're
limiting the alpha level to .05 goes out the window, if you do
that, right. So people are not really aware of the reality that
if you don't follow null hypothesis significance testing
completely and and if you if you make some kind of weird hybrid
version of null hypothesis significance testing and interpreting
p-values as effect sizes and things like that, then essentially,
you should not be pretending that you're using null hypothesis
significance testing, because the problem is that you make it
look like you are actually using a principled version of null
hypothesis significance testing, when actually you are you are
moving the goalposts, right? And, and you are, so you are
claiming that something is evidence for your alternative
hypothesis, because you were able to reject the null hypothesis,
when actually the way you were able to reject the null
hypothesis is by not following the rules for the test as they
were set up, or as they should have been set up, right? Okay, so
you must correct for each test that you do on the data, even if
you are just peeking at the data, unless you are prepared to
completely and utterly disregard the test pretended didn't
happen 20 participants, you run the test just to see what
happens, you get a significant result. And you are prepared to
completely ignore that pretended it didn't happen, or treat it
as, "Well, it was funny, it if I had decided to just run 20
participants, I would have found a significant result. But I
didn't. So I don't have a significant result. And I'm completely
fine with that, because I made my rule to stop after 40
participants. And so what happened after 20 participants is
completely irrelevant for my test now." That is the kind of
attitude that you have to have with null hypothesis significance
testing. And that is what people criticise about it.
Okay, so now talking about the Type II error rate or beta (the
probability). So that is the probability that you fail to reject
the null hypothesis even though it is actually false. So there
is an effect, but your experiment failed to detect it. And as I
said before, the opposite of beta is power, the probability that
you correctly reject the null hypothesis given that it is
actually false. So how do you estimate power? Well, first of
all, you need to determine the critical test statistic for
rejecting your null hypothesis. So that could be a t statistic,
for example. So, this uses your assumption of how results will
be distributed given that the null hypothesis is true, and it
will depend on your chosen alpha. So for example, if you if your
test distribution is of F distributions or a standard normal
distribution, and you have a two tailed test, then your critical
test statistic will be -1.96 or +1.96. And then you make you
need to make some additional assumptions about the alternative
hypothesis because Now, for determining power, you not only have
to make one, use or make one mathematical model, so one use one
probability distribution for the non hypothesis, but you need to
have a second probability distribution for the alternative
hypothesis. And usually, of course, you would assume that the
shape of the distribution is going to be the same. So the same
distribution as for the null hypothesis, usually some kind of a
normal distribution, right, or t-distribution, just with a
different mean, okay, and you would usually also assume that it
has the same variance or the same standard deviation as the
distribution for the null hypothesis, just that it is shifted to
one side to the left or to the right. Okay. So, for example,
let's assume that you want to test the effect of a new
depression treatment on mood. So let's just, let's just deal
with mood variable, let's just assume that you know, the, the
distribution of your measure. So let's say mood is normally
distributed with a standard deviation of four, let's just assume
that to make things easier, okay. So and you say you would be
satisfied with your treatment if it increased mood by at least
four units on the scale. Okay. So if participants mood goes up
by one standard deviation, which is quite a big effect, you
would be happy with the treatment. And let's just hypothetically
say that you don't really care if it improves mood by less. So
in that case, you can use you can use this as a basis of
calculating your power. So you want to have the power of
detecting an effect of one standard deviation. And that's what
Cohen's d is: you just calculate it by taking your difference,
so, subtracting the, the mean, ggiven the null hypothesis --
Sorry, subtracting the mean, given the null hypothesis from the
mean, given the alternative hypothesis, so in this case, the
mean, given the null hypothesis is zero; the mean given the
alternative hypothesis is four, because we said we want to see
mood improvement by four points, right, and then you divide by
the standard deviation. So then you get 4/4=1. Okay, so so that
would be the simplest possible way of doing this. So so let's
say so the distribution you're sampling from, you know, what,
you know, the mean, and you know, the standard deviation, and
then you can calculate, and then you just say I want to detect
an effect size of one. Okay, and if you remember, in G*Power,
you also have to state the effect size that you want to detect,
of course. Okay, so let's say that you have 16. So you have 16
participants. And so, the null hypothesis is that this group of
16 participants comes from this same distribution with a mean of
zero and a standard deviation of 4, okay. So, remember, when we
are taking when we are calculating means,
then these means come from distribution of the, of the means are
sampling distribution of the mean, right. And that has the same
mean as the distribution you're sampling from, and, but smaller
standard deviation, which is also called the standard error of
the mean, okay, and the standard error of the mean, is the
standard deviation of the distribution that you're sampling
from, divided by the square root of the number of observations
in each sample. So fall, in this case, 4 over the square root of
16 is 4/4, and it's 1. So I chose these numbers of course to
make the math As easy as possible. So that means that for a two
tailed test, since we are since our distribute sampling
distribution of the mean that we are sampling from just happens
to be the standard normal distribution, right? Our critical set
value for rejecting the null hypothesis is 1.96. And, of course,
if you were sampling from a different distribution, you would,
you could just look this up. Okay, so you can just, you could
just use Excel, for example, to look at what your critical value
would be in that case. Okay, so if the alternative hypothesis is
true, we assume that the sample from the 16 participants will
come from a normal distribution with a mean of four, and the
standard error, that is also one. Okay, so we can so now, of
course, this is no longer the standard normal distribution. And
we can just, we can just look this up in a table, although it's
not that much different from the standard normal distribution.
The good thing is, we can just check in we can excel can
calculate probabilities for any kind of distribution. So any
kind of normal distribution. So what we want to know is, what is
the probability under this alternative distribution, that we get
a sample with a mean that is lower than our critical value?
Because in that case, if, if our mean is lower than the critical
value, we would fail to reject the null hypothesis, even though
now we are looking at the distribution where the null hypothesis
is objectively false, because this distribution has a mean of
four and not of zero. So given a mean of four, given that the
null hypothesis is false, given that the mean is actually four
and not zero, what is the probability of still only getting a
critical that value here? Of 1.96? Okay, and we can ask Excel
for that. So I'm just going to pull up Excel here. And let's
take a look. So what we want here is we want to know, what is
the probability of getting a value of 1.96 from a normal
distribution with a mean of four and the standard deviation of
one. So I can write here =NORM.DIST. And that returns the normal
distribution for the specified mean, and standard deviation.
Okay, we would like that. Okay. And then then it says here, "x".
So that is the value that the or the cutoff value that we want
to get the area to the left of for the distribution. Okay. So
1.96, comma, and then the mean of this distribution -- 4 -- then
the standard deviation, we said 1, and then the last one is, do
you want the cumulative distribution? Or do you want just the
probability density function? For our purposes, if we want the
area under the curve, we always want cumulative? The cumulative
distribution function, okay, we always want true in this case.
Okay. So here, we are getting .020675. Okay, so the value of
1.96 only cuts off about 2% of the distribution given that the
null hypothesis is false. And the alternative hypothesis that
the mean is actually 4 is true.
Okay, so we can get rid of Excel. So yeah, so this tells us
again, this is just with rounding. So it's .021, beta is .021.
So the power is 1 - .021. And that gives us .9799 or rounded
again, 98%. Okay, so this is so I think, maybe you've seen the
principle, but it is always nice to have a visualisation for
this And someone called Kristoffer Magnusson actually made a
great visual visualisation for this, which I have the link to
here. So you can we can replicate our analysis here. And then we
can try different values. So what happens if we increase or
decrease sample size, we can find out what sample size we need
for our power of .8. What happens if we use reduce alpha to
.025? So let's start with the just replicating the analysis.
Okay, so here's that website. And so here, this is the
visualisation. So you can see that this, this makes things
possibly a lot clearer. So what we just were trying to get was
power. Okay, so we said we wanted an effect size of Cohen's d of
1. So here we go. Oh, now it's .97. Here's 1. Okay. We said we
had a sample size of 16. And we wanted a significance level of
.05, and we would like to have a two tailed right. So this is
exactly what we just calculated using Excel. Only that here you
have it now, nicely visualised. Okay, so here, and and you know,
even you can even hover over it over some of the areas and it
will tell you, so, this, the dotted line is the distribution
given that the null hypothesis is true. Okay, so we're doing a
two tailed test. So it's centred on zero. And we're doing a two
tailed test. So the rejection regions are to the left, and to
the right. So this the area, the red area, here is alpha, the
two areas together, okay, then, here, we have the critical set
value, which we know. In our case, which we know. In our case,
well, here, this is just scaled a little bit differently,
because we don't have we have this being a standard normal
distribution as well. So of the distribution here, but
essentially, this is the critical that value here. And it cuts
off exactly 2% of the distribution given the alternative
hypothesis. And all the other area on the distribution here
giving the alternative hypothesis is power. So the area this,
this area, the shaded in blue, and this includes the this thing
shaded in red here, because this is just in front of it, right.
So all of this (area under the curve) until here, the critical
z-value, gives us the power. Okay, so power, beta, and alpha.
And now we can see how things change. So wow do things change,
if we reduce the sample size to, let's say, eight. So you can
see, by reducing the sample size, the distributions of the mean
of the sample mean get wider, because remember you there, we're
dividing by the square root of the sample size to determine the
standard error, so, the greater the sample size, the smaller the
standard error, and the narrower the distributions are going to
be. So you can see now we have a lot more overlap here, beta is
a lot greater alpha is still the same at 5% Right, but now the
price of having an alpha of 5% is having a beta of 19%. So by
reducing the number of participants from 16 to eight, our
beta goes up from 2% to 19%. Okay, and we can also take a look
at what happens if you change the significance level. So if we
go down to we can't do .025, but we can do .03, right. So what
happens so just to give you the comparison, what happens is, if
you cut off a smaller part of the My extreme parts only have the
distribution given that the null hypothesis is true. That means
that the criterion moves to the right, and also cuts off a
bigger part of the alternative distribution. So that means beta
goes up. Right, so now we have 20%. Beta. If we reduce this to
.01 it goes even further, and we have 40%. Beta, right? While
the type one error is, of course, no one now, because for the
type one error, we only have this tiny little bit, you can't
even hover over that, (it is) so tiny, the alpha. But the price
of that was a reduction in power. Okay. And this is, of course,
for a large effect size. Let's, let's go back to .05. And let's
reset the zoom so we can see all of the distributions. So if we
reduce the effect size, that means, let's see if you are
prepared for what's going to happen. Think about what's going to
happen if I reduce the effect size, what part of the plot is
going to change? Okay. All right. So that's what's going to
change. Did you expect this that the distributions would be
closer together? If so, well done. So yeah, so now we have an
effect size of only half a standard deviation. So Cohen's d
equals .5. And now, you can see with this smaller effect size,
now the distributions overlap quite a lot. And now actually, we
only have a power of 29%. How could we get the power greater
again, well, we could increase the sample size, let's say we go
to 30. Okay, and resetting the zoom, so you can see better, so
that makes the distributions narrower. And now, because they are
narrower, they overlap less. And that also means that the
proportion cut off by the critic criterion from the alternative
distribution is now lower again, so 22%. Similarly, as you can,
you can use this to solve for other things. So. So for example,
if we, so how many participants do we need, in this case, let's
say we wanted a power in this case of .95. So we can just adjust
the slider. And so we would have the distributions, they would
have to be so narrow, that only 5% of the area under the
alternative distribution is smaller than the criteria. And of
course, 2.5% here and 2.5% here, that's that is just the alpha
level, right? So so beta here is controlled as 95% but it means
our sample size goes up quite a bit. So 51.98. And since we
can't have .98 of a participant in practice, it would have to be
52 participants right. And so, you can you can just play with
this a little bit or you can you can see, I have a sample size
of 80 and I want I want alpha of .05 and power of .95, so what
is the smallest the smallest effect size that I can detect with
this? And the answer is .4, Cohen's d of .4. Okay. So this is
quite useful for you to play with, and see how the, how the different
how the different parameters here of the of the test affect the
outcome given that the null hypothesis is true, and given that
the null hypothesis is not. Okay. And so, just to just to go
back to our example, from the slides, so, if we have again, at
Cohen's d of one and we want a power of .8, then we would need
-- let's just reset the zoom -- then we would need a sample size
of 7.85. So, 8, right, if that is what we wanted. Okay, good. So
let's move on. So of course, in reality, we don't have that
distribution. In reality, we have to estimate the the standard
deviation of the population and the standard deviation of the
sampling distribution using the standard deviation of the
sample. And as we said last week, This forces us to use the t
distribution. Okay, so let's say, let's say we still want to
find a Cohen's d of one. But now, we have two groups in a t
test. And we want to calculate power, given our 16 participants,
so eight per group. And what the power is, given Cohen's d of 1
and an alpha level of .05, so let's go to G*Power. Okay, so
there it is. And now we have a t-test, again, so we want to get
our two independent means, okay. And now the type of power
analysis that we want is compute achieved power. So we want to
see, what power do we have, in this case with a sample size of
eight and Group one, and eight in Group two? Of course, we want
two tailed tests. And we want an effect size of 1. So let's
calculate that. And you can see we achieve a power of .461. So
46% power, or a beta of about 53.8%. Okay. Okay. So what does a
significant result actually tell us? And, and we got to that a
little bit when we talked about the statements in the seminar
activity last week, so, but I want to talk about it a little bit
more in terms of multiple studies. And so what do we and also in
terms of, if you if you actually got to in the seminar activity
if you got to the exercise on sensitivity and specificity? And
so, in terms of this of diagnosticity of a test, right? So, what
proportion of significant p values is actually due to a false
positive? And this is not. So again, if you if you paid
attention in the in the seminar, for Question 1, you will, you
will probably be a little bit more careful now. So, what
proportion of significant p values is actually due to a false
positive? If you want to say, .05, then, well, you are right,
given that the null hypothesis is true, but we actually don't
know if the null hypothesis is true or not. Right. So, if,
depending on depending on whether the null hypothesis -- if the
hypothesis is false, then well, then, of course,
the significant p value is not due to a false positive, right.
So, in reality, the significant pair of p values that we get are
a mix of false positives and true positives. Right. So, how do
we get the number of true positives? And, again, if you want to
go back and look at question three of the seminar activity last
week, to see the parallels here, that would be a very neat
exercise for you to do if you if you have the time. If not, I
don't blame you. Okay, so let's make some assumptions. Let's
assume we have an alpha of .05, we have a power of .8. And now
we are looking at 200 studies. And again, going back to that
question 3 on "What's the probability that I have COVID given a
positive test?" This is very similar. What's the probability
that I have that I have found an actual difference in the world
based on my significant result, compared to the probability that
this is a false positive? And I have actually, and actually,
there is no true difference in the world. Okay. So, if you
remember, you had to assume that you had to in question three,
you have to assume something about the base rate. So what
percentage of people with symptoms actually have COVID. And like
that, we also have to assume similar something about hypotheses.
So let's say, in psychology, 50%, of all hypotheses that are
tested are actually true. And then it's actually quite high. So
that would mean that people are very good at making hypotheses.
But let's just say it's 50%. So then, if we are looking at 200
studies, at 200 t tests, right, from from 200 different studies,
then then 100 of them test a hypothesis that's actually true.
And 100 of them test a hypothesis that's actually false. And so
let's take, let's take a look at this, then let's fill in this
table. So we know that we're using an alpha level of .05, right.
So in this case, 95. So if the null hypothesis is true, we will
not reject and correctly not reject the null hypothesis in 95,
out of the 100 studies, and we will incorrectly reject the null
hypothesis and five out of those out of those 100 studies,
right, and the percentage that you have behind there is what
percentage this is of the total of 200 studies. Okay, so then,
if the null hypothesis is all is actually false, and the
alternative hypothesis is true. So again, we have 100 studies
where that is the case, then. So here, we have to make another
assumption, we have to assume that our studies have a power of
.8, right? So in this case, which is quite high. So in this
case, we reject the null, like, we correctly reject the null
hypothesis for 80 out of the 100 studies, where the null
hypothesis is actually false, and we fail to reject it
incorrectly. So committing a type two error in 20, out of the
100 studies. Okay. So let's so now let's take a look at at the
percentages here. And again, go back to go back to Question
three, if you want to see the parallel of this to the COVID test,
because you're making the same kind of table. Okay, so we have
85 significant tests. So 5+80=85. These are significance test
significant tests, where the test rejects the null hypothesis.
Okay? So out of those 85 significant tests, five are false
positives. So five divided by 85 is 5.88%. And we call this the
false positive rate. I mentioned this in the seminar, as well in
the well in the seminar slides, at least if you didn't get to
the question. And then 80 of the 85 significant tests are true
positives. So that's one minus basically -- well, it's in terms
of percentages 100 minus the false positive rate. So this is the
positive predictive value. And these team terms were coined by
John Ioannides this in a research paper that got a lot of
attention, you can click on this and and read it. Unfortunately,
John iron ideas has, well, he has maybe well, he's he's sort of
gone out of his area of expertise recently with with COVID. So
If you're interested in that, look it up it has sort of damaged
the the image that a lot of people had of him. Similar to quite
similar to Daryl -- to what happened with Daryl Bem. Right. So
So I guess everyone has their particular area where they may be,
well, where they may be a little bit outside of what, what would
possibly be a reasonable position. But anyway, in this paper was
very well received. And it was actually about the false positive
rate in medicine. And in medicine, the situation is actually a
bit better than in psychology because at least there you have
clinical studies that are pre registered, and very carefully
controlled double blind studies, which in psychology, we tend to
do very little of those kind of double blind studies where the
experimenter also doesn't know which group the participant is
in, or what condition the the participant is working. But still,
his conclusion was in their paper, that the state of testing in
medicine was quite worrying with a high false positive rate, and
a much lower positive predictive value than you would want in
something as important as clinical testing. So why is this a
problem, so maybe you didn't find this results in the table to
be looking so bad, I mean, false positive rate of 5.88. That's
not, that's not terrible. But that is also assuming that making
some assumptions that maybe aren't that that realistic. So there
is a an interactive visualisation of the false positive rate by
Felix Schönbrodt, which I have the link of here. So first, we
are going to take a look at the situation that I put in the
table as an example. And then we can explore other situations.
And there's also an option called the percentage of pßhacked
studies. And I will talk about that in a second. So those are
studies where people, for example, do things like multiple
testing, or without correcting for it, and that just turns
values that should be, or tests that should be non-significant
into significant tests, because of problems with just applying
the null hypothesis significance testing method, and a nice and
short way of calling this is p-hacking. So hacking in the sense
of, I am sort of messing with the system of null hypothesis
significance testing, until I get what I want, which could be
one one definition of hacking in software as well.
Okay, so let's take a look at the visualisation now. And as you
can see, this is called when does a significant p-value indicate
a true effect, understanding the positive predictive value of a
p-value? Okay, so on the left side, you have the parameters of
the simulation. So you've got percent of a-priori true
hypotheses. So this, this means how many prior how many
hypotheses that we make, for example, in psychology are actually
true. Before we do that, so (how many) are actually true and how
many are false; here it's set to 30. Let's, let's assume the
same thing as in the table and set it to 50. Then alpha level
.05, we'll leave that do we want to specify power directly or
indirectly through sample size and effect size, we can specify
it here directly, we can set it to 2.8. The number of p hat
studies, we will leave that at zero for now. Okay? So and you
can see we've replicated the results from the table. Right? So
40% true positives 10% false negatives 47.5%, true negatives
2.5% false positives. So that gives us a positive predict. The
value of 95.1% and a false discovery rate of 5.9%. So, yeah,
just what, what we found, and in this visualisation, so each
point is one study here. So the false positives are in red, the
true negatives are in yellow, the true positives are in green,
and the false negatives are in blue. Okay, so here you can see,
in this case, with 80%, power, 50% true hypotheses, alpha of
.05, or 5%. Most of the studies are either true negatives or
true positives. There are some false negatives. So remember,
power is just .8, so 20%, false negatives, and a small number of
false positives, because alpha is at .05, so 5%. If we only
consider the significant findings, the ratio of true to false
positives looks like this: Right? So now we're taking all the
negatives out the true and the false negatives, and just
consider the relationship between true and false positives. And
there are many more false positives, of course, than true
positives. All right. I think I just reset, just reset the page,
but not a problem. Okay, here we got it. Again, it just went
back to the default values. Okay, so now, now we can try this
out a little bit. So, so yeah, so if we, let's say we still have
power of point eight, but now only 30% of a-priori true
hypotheses. So then most hypotheses are false here, so you got
more yellow and red. And because you've got more, because you've
got more positive, more, more false hypothesis. In general, of
course, you also have more false positives, you have fewer false
negatives, because you have fewer negative few negatives. And,
of course, you have also fewer true positives. So with this,
now, our our false positives have gone up a little and our true
positives have gone down. So now 12% of all claimed findings are
actually false positives. And we can keep doing this. We can
also say, Well, now let's set it to 50% power, which is more of
maybe what happens in psychology. So that means we have more
false negatives, now, we have even fewer true positives. So that
means that now we have a false discovery rate of 18.9%. Okay, so
now, adding to this p-hacked studies, let's say, let's say 10%
of studies contain questionable research practices. So now, now
10% of the yellow points have turned red. So they have become
false positives, instead of true negatives. So now we have
we have many more false positives, and the number of true
positives hasn't actually changed. So now, we are at a scenario
where failure where 38.1% of claim findings are false. And so so
out of out of every 10 papers that you're looking at, in there
now for our faults. And so in the paper by Ioannides you've got
different scenarios, so like, registered clinical trial, with
little bias. So there you would have 15% of claim findings that
are false. You could also switch it to for example, a poorly
performed clinical trial where the assumption is that 80% of all
results are p-hacked. So then there we would have 82% of claim
findings that are false. In psychology, we would probably have
something hopefully, like, an adequately powered, exploratory
study. So well, exploratory means most of your hypotheses are
false. Because you're just exploratory in this case means you're
just trying different things, see what sticks. It's adequately
powered, it has point eight. But we still have p-hacked study.
So even if we go with p-hacked studies to zero -- oh no, it's
100 now -- now, let's go to set p-hacked studies to zero, even
then, in this case, we have only, we have still 38.7% of claimed
findings false. And if we set the number of px studies to 30,
then again, we have 80% of claimed findings that are false. So
it is really, it is a bit of a scary visualisation here to see,
depending on how optimistic or pessimistic we are about the
percentage of true hypotheses, for example, and the level of pee
hacking. Maybe most of the research that's published is actually
false. Right? Now, people are probably going to have questions
about the percentage of true hypotheses. And you're right, that
this is something that is not completely clear how you arrive at
this value. I mean, the replication project in psychology had
was able to replicate maybe between 30 and 40%, I think it was
something like 38% or 37%, of all of the studies. So if we have
that, and we have a power of .8, and we are very hopeful that
only problems only exist in 10% of all studies, then well, then
maybe only 23% of claim findings are false. But that is still
more than one in five, right? So it is, so it is a problem. And
I hope this visualisation helps you a little bit in in seeing
the scale of magnitude of the problem. Okay, so, so going back
to our presentation, just to to address the question of how does
p-hacking happen? We have already said multiple comparisons
without controlling. In general, when you perform an experiment,
or any kind of study, you have what's called experiment the
degrees of freedom. And if you watched the video by Andrew
Gelman that I had in the lecture one materials, then he talks
about the multiverse of possible data analyses. So there are a
lot and there are lots of things that you can do with your data.
So do you aggregate the data in a particular way? Do you add a
control variable? Do you enter something as a continuous
variable or as a discrete variable? So do you do things like a
median split, to split a continuous variable into high and low,
and all of those things affect the outcome of the data analysis,
and all of these can lead to false positives. If you if you do
things like, Well, if you if you try different ones, different
versions of analysing the data, and then just stick with the one
that has,
that manages to reject the null hypothesis. And if you listen to
this now, as someone who has probably never done a study before
sat, but some of you will do a study, or maybe you've done your
psychology project, but possibly that was not significant.
Anyway. So you might not have had this problem. But it's very
easy to get into this kind of mindset where you say, "Well, I, I
am quite sure that my hypothesis is actually true. My
alternative, my experimental hypothesis is actually true. And I
just need to find so if I if I don't find it, if I don't find it
in my analysis, then I must be doing something wrong. So I need
to change my analysis, sort of learn from my data and tweak my
analysis until I find what I think must be there". And this is a
very dangerous attitude, but it is also very understandable in
people who are doing experiments, especially for the first time.
And unfortunately, I think in some people, it just this attitude
just persists because no one ever tells them any better. They
don't, they just don't know better. They think that their
analysis choices are justified by the outcomes that they're
finding an effect that they think is there anyway. Because
that's what they believe, like power posing it. If you think
about it enough, I think if you work about it, if you work on
it, for long enough, you really develop a very strong conviction
that it is real, that it is a true effect. And then you will,
and then from there, too, I'm not saying that Amy Cuddy did
this. I don't know, I haven't looked at it in that much detail,
right?. I've been I've read the analysis that other people had
of their work. But then it is very easy to get into the mindset
of saying, if I'm not finding the effect, I'm doing something
wrong, so I'm trying different things until I get it right,
which is finding the effect. And that is a problem, of course.
Another thing is HARKing hypothesising, after the results are
no. So that would be something like saying, Okay, I am studying
depression, I am really interested in,
in the mood variable. But I don't find anything there. So now
I'm thinking, "Hmm, what, what, what about sleep quality?"
And maybe I go back to my participants, and I have them do a
sleep quality, sleep quality measure. And then I test that, and,
and, oh, is that suddenly significant? Or maybe if it's not
significant, maybe I go back and try another measure, maybe I
try to split by, by gender. Or maybe I tried to split by
socioeconomic status and things like that, right. And all of
these, so all of these hypotheses, I'm coming up with hypotheses
based on my data, and not based on the theory. And that is also
very dangerous. Because if you use the same data, to confirm
your hypotheses that you've used to come up with it, that is not
a proper test that because then you are going to find, you're
going to find your effect, because you're studying it on the
very same data where you have observed the effect, right? The
point is, or the the idea is that you do exploration, maybe on
one datasets, you just look at everything that's in one data set
and say, Oh, look, there's a difference in gender. And then you
try to replicate it in a different data set. So (in terms of)
exploratory and confirmatory research, HARKing, is mixing,
exploratory and confirmatory research. Okay, then we already
talked about multiple comparisons without controlling for them.
And then, of course, you could also have assumption violations
so that you just do the test, you just do a test that is not
appropriate for your data. But really, that is usually fairly
well policed by peer review. First of all, because it's an easy
objective thing to criticise your study on. And secondly, the
effects of assumption violations. And we'll talk about this
later in, in this unit. But the effects of assumption violations
compared to the effects of experimental degree of freedom,
harking, multiple comparisons, just p-hacking in general, are so
tiny, that actually, it's hard for me to think of a study that
had a false positive due to an assumption violation, but plenty
of studies that had false positives due to HARKing, experimenter
degrees of freedom, things like that, that did not replicate
because of that, not because you did the wrong analysis on
analysis, that wasn't appropriate. And the funny thing is that
in undergraduate psychology statistics, I hope it's changing,
but but at least it used to be that you would spend endless time
on assumption violations and just ignoring p-hacking
experimented degrees of freedom. Maybe you talked a little bit
about Bonferroni corrections, but that was pretty much it.
Right? So you spend a lot of time on on small on a small issue.
assumption violations. We'll talk about it later. How, for
example, with tests like ANOVA, they are so robust that many
assumption violations don't really change the outcome. So you
spend a lot of time on those, but you spend very little time on
the actual problems, which is, which are p-hacking, underpowered
studies? Bad hypothesising, those other kinds of things that
that cause real problems in psychology and with replicability.
So again, we've already we've played through this on the
visualisation, so I'm not going to go back to that now. But if
we put in 40% of hypotheses that are true, so so this is
generous, right? average power is .5, it might be lower 10% of
studies or P hacked, then we get a false discovery rate of 28.3.
And so between 1 in 4 and 1 in 3 psychology studies with
significant results are actually false. And if you make more
pessimistic assumptions, then you would get a worse picture and
now relevant for your assignment, for the coursework. For the
essay, try playing with the alpha slider, try seeing what
happens when you go from .05 to .005, and I'm not going to tell
you what happens, you have to try it and then and then see if
you can use that for your essay.
Okay. So then finally, so I in the past lectures and workshops
and seminars, I have often hinted at the fact that Fisher caused
the problem with his approach to the interpretation of p values.
So Fisher's conception of probability was somewhere between
subjective and objective. And he did not like like, name and
Pearson's approach. In fact, they hated each other so much that
Neyman and Pearson moved from the UK to the US, just to be far
away from Fisher. Well, I'm sure there were other reasons, but I
think it was a major reason, they really didn't like each other.
So in Fishers opinion, a p value of.01 provides more evidence
against the null hypothesis, then a p value of .05. And because
Fisher was very influential, people started imitating this. The
problem is that Fisher never claimed to be doing all hypothesis
significance testing. And the problem is that people started
conflating the strict null hypothesis significance testing that
Neyman and Pearson proposed with Fisher's approach to using p
values as an an indication of evidence or effect size of
strength of evidence. And the two things just don't go together,
you can either do one or the other. But people started
pretending that they're doing null hypothesis significance
testing, but mixing it up with, with ideas from Fischer, and
that, that led to the problematic situation where we, that we
are in now. So the rejection rules are strict for a reason. If
you don't do non hypothesis significance testing in a principled
way, you are not going to get the outcome that you think you're
getting, but you are then communicating it as if you had been
following the rules. So in general, using p values as measures
of evidence is a bad idea. And we have better ways of doing
that, using Bayesian methods. I will see that in the next
lecture. So finally, to summarise our criticism of null
hypothesis significance testing: First, it is inflexible and
offers only black and white decisions. And it offers only two
decisions. Remember that, right? Only reject a null hypothesis,
or fail to reject the null hypothesis. There's nothing else
there's no accepting the null hypothesis. There is no accepting
the alternative hypothesis. There is no rejecting the
alternative hypothesis. No, there's only rejecting the null
hypothesis or not rejecting the null hypothesis. There is
nothing else. Okay? And that can be a problem. For example, what
if you're actually interested in the null hypothesis? What if
you want to show that there is no difference? No hypothesis
significance testing does not really have a mechanism for that.
And people have sort of tried to do it by doing a test with very
high power, and then saying, Okay, I had extremely high power.
So if an effect was there, I should have found it. But instead I
failed to reject the null hypothesis. And, well, they've that
has sort of worked in the past, but it's not great. Because
you're essentially using the logic of null hypothesis
significance testing and turning it around. Also, the whole
concept of significance. So --and this is something where people
intuitively see that Fisher was of course, right, right, that
that if you get a very low p value, there is something different
about a very low p value, compared to a p value that's close to
.05. Right? There is something different about that. But the
problem is, in non partisan significance testing, you're
supposed to completely ignore that. Because otherwise, your
strict testing rules go out of the window. Okay? So so you can
also understand why people why people would do things like say,
"Oh, this is marginally significant, or this is very
significant," right? highly significant. If you're using null
hypothesis significance testing, do not use terms like highly
significant, or almost significant, or marginally significant or
close to significance. There is no such such thing. They're
significant, and there is not significant. That's all there is.
But of course, people feel that, that doesn't quite describe
what they're seeing. And that is the problem. So you can also
say that, well, the focus on null hypotheses limits the amount
of thinking that researchers do about the alternative
hypotheses. So usually, I mean, you have to, you only have to
specify the alternative hypothesis a little bit if you want to,
if you want to find out power, because for that you need you
need some kind of idea about what your alternative hypothesis
is, if you haven't cared about power, then you don't need to
think about what the alternative hypothesis is at all. So that,
and as a result, you're usually what you see the alternative
hypotheses that you see, are very, very vague. Most hypotheses
are also just not realistic. It's very unlikely in nature for
anything to be exactly zero. It may the true difference may well
be very close to zero. But it's unlikely to have an exact that
things are exactly exactly exactly the same. So that's, that is
an issue. So in a way, the knowledge hypothesis is this kind of
straw man, that doesn't really that isn't even realistic. So
then, of course, we have the familywise error rate. So the
problem with this is, what is the reference class here. And the
problem is that it depends on what you were planning on doing.
So if you have a t-test with p = .04, if this is the only t-test
you plan on doing, it is significant. The exact same result, if
you're planning on doing a second t-test, is no longer
significant. So unless you write down very clearly, what you are
planning on doing, it's very easy to just trick yourself into
thinking, "Oh, I wasn't actually going to run that second
t-test," even though you would have absolutely run the second T
test if the first one hadn't resulted significant. Right. So and
with stopping rules, it gets even more extreme. So if you have
one scientist, that tests 30 participants and another scientist
that tests 30 participants. If the first scientist, checked the
data at 15 participants would have stopped, but didn't. And the
second part, the second scientist didn't check the data, then
they could have the exact exact same means the exact same
results, but one would have a significant result. So the one who
didn't stop and peek, and the other one would have a
nonsignificant result. And that is a problem. That doesn't
really make a lot of sense. So in the next lecture, we will talk
about an alternative to null hypothesis significance testing,
just Bayesian statistics and maybe you We'll find that these are
a lot more intuitive compared to what we've done now. But it is
of course important to talk about another hypothesis
significance testing, because that's what almost everyone is
doing today. Bayesian statistics is sort of gaining, but there's
still a long way to go. Still most studies report p values.
Okay. And that is it for this week. Thank you very much for
listening.