Okay, hello, and welcome to our
third lecture on the limits of
knowledge hypothesis
significance testing. So, in the
past few lectures, you've
probably, at least had some
reason to think about what the
problems are with null
hypothesis significance testing,
so not just the problems due to
incorrect use of null hypothesis
significance testing, although
those are definitely there and
definitely an issue, but also
the general issues with null
hypothesis significance testing,
with this particular method of
trying to get evidence for a
particular hypothesis. Okay, so
we've already mentioned in the
previous lecture, type one error
and type two error. So type one
error is when you reject the
null hypothesis, even though it
is true, and the probability of
that is called alpha. A type two
error is when you fail to reject
the null hypothesis even though
it is false. And the alternative
hypothesis which is here called
H1 is true. And the probability
of making this error is called
beta. Now, of course, if not, if
this is true, and we are not
rejecting it, then that is a
correct decision. And if you
have looked at the some of the
problems in the seminar activity
for last week, then you might
also see that this, the
probability of making this
correct decision is for
diagnostic test is called
specificity. Okay. And then
finally, the other correct
decision that you can make is to
reject the null hypothesis. If
it is actually false, and the
alternative hypothesis is true.
The probability of doing this is
called power, and then a
diagnostic test. This would be
known as sensitivity. Okay, so
we want to avoid a type one
error. Right? So how do you
control it? Well, first of all,
we control the type one error
rate directly because of the way
no hypothesis significance
testing works, by just setting
alpha to an appropriate level.
And usually we're using .05,
right. But there are many
factors that can increase the
type one error rate, and we saw
one in our first workshop
question for last week, if you
remember, we talked about if we
have my many tests, and each
individual test has a type one
error rate on alpha level of
.05, how do these individual
alphas add up to the whole
family, or in the whole family
of tests. And that is, for
example, a problem when you do
neuroscience. And when you
analyse brain areas, and you
want to compare lots of
activation and lots of different
brain areas, and you are ready
to reject your null hypothesis
that maybe is just nothing
changes in the brain, I don't
really care about which area, I
just care at my normal
processes, it's just I can see I
will not see the effect
anywhere. And then I have 40
different areas. And I do 40
different t-tests on brain
activation in those areas. So in
this case, I definitely have to
control the error, or control
the alpha, because so you did
this in the workshop for for 40
comparisons, right. And you
remember it was about the
probability was about 87%, of
making at least one type one
error in the 40 tests. The more
tests you make, of course, the
closer the probability gets to
100. And that is just, if I have
a test that has a 5% probability
built in of making an error,
then the more often I do the
test, the more often I'm going
to get the error. So even if, if
for a single test, right down
here, it's quite low. Even for
two tests, that's already above
point oh five, right. And if I
make many tests, I mean, even if
I do -- if I have just 20 tests
-- we already have a Type I
error rate of about 60% Alright,
so you need to control for this.
Otherwise, you're going to make
a mistake. If what you're doing
is, you have one, no hypothesis
that you would reject. Given any
significant result of any of
these tests, it's important to
keep in mind if you if you have
two different hypotheses, and
you do two t tests, and each one
tests a completely different
hypothesis. And t test number
two does not affect hypothesis
number one, then you don't have
a test family, and then you
don't have to correct right, it
is about rejecting one null
hypothesis, but you have
multiple ways of rejecting it,
because you're doing multiple
comparisons. Okay. So this is
called the family-wise Type I
error rate. And as I just said,
a family of hypothesis tests is
a number of tests that would
each on their own, lead you to
reject one single null
hypothesis. So for example,
let's say you're testing the
intervention on depression, and
you want to see if the treatment
group differs from the control
group in terms of mood,
activity, and sleep quality. So
you're measuring these three
dependent variables for each of
the sort of the difference in
these variables for each of the
four, the control group and the
treatment group. And you conduct
one t-test each for for each of
these measures. So your
hypothesis is just that the
intervention has an effect, you
don't care about whether the
effect is on mood, activity,
sleep quality, a combination of
two of them, all three of them,
you're happy, if it makes any
difference at all, okay, in this
case, those three tests form a
test family, because you will
reject the overall hypothesis
that says my treatment has no
effect. If any of those three t
tests become significant, and
then you can just calculate what
would the family-wise Type I
error rate be? In this scenario,
so you have three tests with an
alpha of 5%, of point oh five,
and you're going to reject the
overall hypothesis, no matter
which one of those tests reaches
significance, or maybe two, or
maybe three, could could be any
of those cases. And, as we've
talked about, in the workshop
last week, and as we talked
about in the previous slide,
this probability is one minus
point nine, five, cube so to the
third power, and that gives us
point 143. So 14.3% probability
of rejecting the null
hypothesis, even if it is true.
So even if there is absolutely
no true difference, in any of
these three variables, we have a
14% probability of rejecting the
null hypothesis and committing a
type one error. Okay, and that
is no longer that is no longer
our 5% Alpha. Right? So if we
said, oh, yeah, 5% probability
of, of incorrectly rejecting the
null hypothesis I'm okay with
with that, right. But now we
have a 14.3% probability of
incorrectly rejecting the null
hypothesis. So what can we do
about this. And the easiest way
to controlling the familywize
type one error rate, but also
the most radical way, is the
Bonferroni correction. And if
you've done undergraduate
statistics, you have heard of
that.
What you do for the Bonferroni
correction is you simply use a
different alpha. So you lower
the alpha level by dividing it
by the number of tests. And you
can see that it works. So if we
in this case, we use an alpha of
point oh five divided by three.
So point oh five is our overall
overall family wide alpha. And
now for each individual test, we
then use an alpha of point o
one, seven. Now, of course, that
makes it harder for us to reject
our null hypothesis. So it
lowers our power, it increases
the probability of a Type two
error. But in general, in Nolet,
prothesis significance testing
we feel that a type one error is
worse than a type two error. So
what we will try to do first is
control the type one error and
then see what the consequences
of this is for Type two error.
So if we look at what this does
to our type one error rate, so
now we have, instead of point oh
5.95, we now have point 983,
some, so one minus point o one,
seven, which is our new
corrected alpha, right? So we
cube that. And so we get point,
oh, four, nine. So it's a little
bit lower, even then our
original alpha of point oh five,
but it's close enough. Because
it is mathematically so easy
that we can, we are fine with
doing it backwards. So although,
of course, for every little bit
that you move the that you lower
the alpha, you increase the
beta, so the probability of
making a type two error, and you
lower your power. So but the
main thing is that with this
correction, our type one error
rate is just below point oh,
five, just like we wanted. Okay,
there are variations of this
correction. So that's the
Bonferroni home correction, for
example, where you say, Okay, I,
I don't correct all the tests
equally, but rather, I, I have,
if I have one test that I
particularly care about, then I
can correct that one less, and
the other ones more, and I still
get the overall Type 1 error
rate that I'm interested in. But
basically, the basic principle
is the same, you sacrifice some
power in order to keep the Type
I error rate controlled. And the
Bonferroni-Holm method, as
opposed to the standard
Bonferroni method, just helps
you do this. So you get the
maximum possible power for the
one comparison, maybe you care
most about. Okay. So that's
multiple comparisons. And and
you need to be honest about what
a multiple or multiple
comparison is. Because often
people are not honest about what
tests are a family. But, for
example, if you're testing eight
variables, and so maybe you
might be, you might be telling
yourself, yeah, I wouldn't, I
wouldn't report this as
significant. If just, if it just
comes out in one of the
variables, it has to come out in
two or something like that. Is
that really what you're going to
do? It is it is a good idea to
actually write down your
decision strategy, and then
stick to it. And we'll we'll be
talking about pre-registration,
a little bit in Lecture five.
But that is part of the idea is,
is that you that you stick to
one decision criterion, so you
can't just move go moving the
goalposts because you say, "Oh,
I thought I was going to find an
effect on mood. But I also
tested sleep quality. And sleep
quality is of course, a
completely different hypothesis.
So now, I'm going to report ---
So I'm going to say, oh, yeah,
this is significant. I'm going
to just pretend that I was
interested in sleep quality to
begin with." That doesn't work;
that is moving the goalposts.
Okay. Multiple comparisons are
not the only way to increase the
type one error rate. So in the
lecture last week, I showed you
an example of an optional
stopping rule. And these
stopping rules the way they work
is -- and this is something that
people used to do all the time.
And in actual research, because
they didn't know any better.
They thought this was fine.
So if you so let's say you have
collected 30 participants, and
you just look and see what what
the data look like. Because it's
in general a good idea to check
what you're actually doing, what
data you're actually collecting.
It's good to check on the data
quality. Sure. And just to make
sure that everything works, you
run the significance test and
you find, yeah, I have a
significant effect. So great. So
you stop data collection, and
you decide to publish the
results with a significant
effect. Now the problem is, if
you don't get a significant
result, what do you do then?
Maybe, and this used to be very,
very common, that when people
went to talk to their
dissertation supervisors, the
supervisor would say, "Oh yeah,
you didn't get any results after
30 participants, oh, well run 10
more people see what happens."
And that is an optional stopping
rule. Because that means if I
had gotten a significant result
after 30, participant, I would
have stopped here. Now I'm
running 40 participants. So now
after 40 participants, if I now
have a significant result, then
I can stop. But if I still don't
have one, maybe I'll run 10
more, maybe I'll go to 50
participants. But you see that
each of these tests, each of
these tests is is a new
comparison. I mean, is the the
thing that makes people feel
better about this is that
they're not, of course, not
completely independent from each
other, because you still have
the 30 participants from the
first test. But you have to
treat this, essentially, as a
new test that you are
performing. And that new test.
Well, at worst has another .05
alpha. Right. So now, with the
optional stuffing rule, you're
again, performing essentially
multiple comparisons, and you're
just picking and choosing the
one that is significant, right?
Maybe when you have a
significant effect, after 30,
then you collect data from some
participants who don't show the
effect. So maybe you just had,
maybe you just had good luck or
bad luck to get a couple of
participants where the effect is
randomly strong. And then you
get, and then the next 10, it's
not going to be very strong. So
after 40 participants, maybe you
wouldn't get the effect
significant anymore. But if you
have stopped collecting the data
after 30, because you found a
significant result, you would
never get to these other
participants, right? So you need
to have a firm stopping rule.
You can say, I'm going to stop
after 40 participant data sets,
no matter what happens, then you
are fine, because then you
perform one test. And and that's
the test that that counts. And
then if you have this firm
stopping roll, of course, you
could peek at the data and say,
"Oh, yeah, if I had stopped
collecting data now, the effect
would be significant. But oh,
well, I need to see what happens
after 40 participants, I can't
just stop at 30, just because
the effect is significant." You
have to be principled like that.
And a lot of people aren't, and
a lot of people don't realise
that it's a big deal, which is
why this is so important. And
especially if the test narrowly
missed significance. So I told
you last week, a p value of
point o seven is for the
purposes of null hypothesis
significance testing is
absolutely no different from a p
value of point nine, nine,
right, it is not significant. It
is not marginal, it is not
almost significant. It is it is
simply not significant. But of
course, people like just like
when you are when you miss the
train by 10 seconds instead of
by 10 minutes. Where the end
result is the same. You're not
on the train, right. But
people find it is much more
frustrating to miss the train by
10 seconds, then by 10 minutes,
because it's much easier to
imagine how it could have
worked. So that is that is one
of the biases that Daniel
Kahneman studied, right. So, of
course, and of course,
psychology researchers are as
vulnerable to these biases as
everyone else. So people say,
Oh, well, I have point oh seven
that is so close to significant.
So if I just run five more
participants, then I'll probably
get insignificant. And maybe
it'll happen. Right? The problem
is that you would have to
collect to correct for making
this decision to collect five
more participants. And that is
correcting for it is quite
tricky. I mean, in the worst
case, you would have to have
your alpha, right, because
you're doing two tests, two
comparisons now. And then of
course, a p value, even if after
five more participants, you get
a P value of point oh five,
that's no longer going to be
significant. So But people
imagine that they don't have to
correct for this. And then, even
worse, let's say it gets the
effect gets a tiny bit stronger
after five more participants,
but it's still not at the
criterion. So P equals point oh
six, we're moving in the right
direction, let's just get some
more participants. And I think
what underlies this problem is
that people correctly feel that
a p-value --- So a result that
leads to a p-value of .06 is not
that different from a result
that leads to a p value of .049.
But if you're doing no
hypothesis significance testing,
it completely changes your
decision. And that is just
because you put the criterion
there, you have to put your
criterion somewhere. Otherwise,
you can't use not hypothesis
significance testing, you have
to have your criterion to reject
or not reject. Right? And
because people naturally see,
well, these results are not that
different. I could easily get
from non significant to
significant event, just add a
few participants. The problem is
that then the whole test
strategy for for null hypothesis
significance testing, but the
whole idea that we're limiting
the alpha level to .05 goes out
the window, if you do that,
right. So people are not really
aware of the reality that if you
don't follow null hypothesis
significance testing completely
and and if you if you make some
kind of weird hybrid version of
null hypothesis significance
testing and interpreting
p-values as effect sizes and
things like that, then
essentially, you should not be
pretending that you're using
null hypothesis significance
testing, because the problem is
that you make it look like you
are actually using a principled
version of null hypothesis
significance testing, when
actually you are you are moving
the goalposts, right? And, and
you are, so you are claiming
that something is evidence for
your alternative hypothesis,
because you were able to reject
the null hypothesis, when
actually the way you were able
to reject the null hypothesis is
by not following the rules for
the test as they were set up, or
as they should have been set up,
right? Okay, so you must correct
for each test that you do on the
data, even if you are just
peeking at the data, unless you
are prepared to completely and
utterly disregard the test
pretended didn't happen 20
participants, you run the test
just to see what happens, you
get a significant result. And
you are prepared to completely
ignore that pretended it didn't
happen, or treat it as, "Well,
it was funny, it if I had
decided to just run 20
participants, I would have found
a significant result. But I
didn't. So I don't have a
significant result. And I'm
completely fine with that,
because I made my rule to stop
after 40 participants. And so
what happened after 20
participants is completely
irrelevant for my test now."
That is the kind of attitude
that you have to have with null
hypothesis significance testing.
And that is what people
criticise about it.
Okay, so now talking about the
Type II error rate or beta (the
probability). So that is the
probability that you fail to
reject the null hypothesis even
though it is actually false. So
there is an effect, but your
experiment failed to detect it.
And as I said before, the
opposite of beta is power, the
probability that you correctly
reject the null hypothesis given
that it is actually false. So
how do you estimate power? Well,
first of all, you need to
determine the critical test
statistic for rejecting your
null hypothesis. So that could
be a t statistic, for example.
So, this uses your assumption of
how results will be distributed
given that the null hypothesis
is true, and it will depend on
your chosen alpha. So for
example, if you if your test
distribution is of F
distributions or a standard
normal distribution, and you
have a two tailed test, then
your critical test statistic
will be -1.96 or +1.96. And then
you make you need to make some
additional assumptions about the
alternative hypothesis because
Now, for determining power, you
not only have to make one, use
or make one mathematical model,
so one use one probability
distribution for the non
hypothesis, but you need to have
a second probability
distribution for the alternative
hypothesis. And usually, of
course, you would assume that
the shape of the distribution is
going to be the same. So the
same distribution as for the
null hypothesis, usually some
kind of a normal distribution,
right, or t-distribution, just
with a different mean, okay, and
you would usually also assume
that it has the same variance or
the same standard deviation as
the distribution for the null
hypothesis, just that it is
shifted to one side to the left
or to the right. Okay. So, for
example, let's assume that you
want to test the effect of a new
depression treatment on mood. So
let's just, let's just deal with
mood variable, let's just assume
that you know, the, the
distribution of your measure. So
let's say mood is normally
distributed with a standard
deviation of four, let's just
assume that to make things
easier, okay. So and you say you
would be satisfied with your
treatment if it increased mood
by at least four units on the
scale. Okay. So if participants
mood goes up by one standard
deviation, which is quite a big
effect, you would be happy with
the treatment. And let's just
hypothetically say that you
don't really care if it improves
mood by less. So in that case,
you can use you can use this as
a basis of calculating your
power. So you want to have the
power of detecting an effect of
one standard deviation. And
that's what Cohen's d is: you
just calculate it by taking your
difference, so, subtracting the,
the mean, ggiven the null
hypothesis -- Sorry, subtracting
the mean, given the null
hypothesis from the mean, given
the alternative hypothesis, so
in this case, the mean, given
the null hypothesis is zero; the
mean given the alternative
hypothesis is four, because we
said we want to see mood
improvement by four points,
right, and then you divide by
the standard deviation. So then
you get 4/4=1. Okay, so so that
would be the simplest possible
way of doing this. So so let's
say so the distribution you're
sampling from, you know, what,
you know, the mean, and you
know, the standard deviation,
and then you can calculate, and
then you just say I want to
detect an effect size of one.
Okay, and if you remember, in
G*Power, you also have to state
the effect size that you want to
detect, of course. Okay, so
let's say that you have 16. So
you have 16 participants. And
so, the null hypothesis is that
this group of 16 participants
comes from this same
distribution with a mean of zero
and a standard deviation of 4,
okay. So, remember, when we are
taking when we are calculating
means,
then these means come from
distribution of the, of the
means are sampling distribution
of the mean, right. And that has
the same mean as the
distribution you're sampling
from, and, but smaller standard
deviation, which is also called
the standard error of the mean,
okay, and the standard error of
the mean, is the standard
deviation of the distribution
that you're sampling from,
divided by the square root of
the number of observations in
each sample. So fall, in this
case, 4 over the square root of
16 is 4/4, and it's 1. So I
chose these numbers of course to
make the math As easy as
possible. So that means that for
a two tailed test, since we are
since our distribute sampling
distribution of the mean that we
are sampling from just happens
to be the standard normal
distribution, right? Our
critical set value for rejecting
the null hypothesis is 1.96.
And, of course, if you were
sampling from a different
distribution, you would, you
could just look this up. Okay,
so you can just, you could just
use Excel, for example, to look
at what your critical value
would be in that case. Okay, so
if the alternative hypothesis is
true, we assume that the sample
from the 16 participants will
come from a normal distribution
with a mean of four, and the
standard error, that is also
one. Okay, so we can so now, of
course, this is no longer the
standard normal distribution.
And we can just, we can just
look this up in a table,
although it's not that much
different from the standard
normal distribution. The good
thing is, we can just check in
we can excel can calculate
probabilities for any kind of
distribution. So any kind of
normal distribution. So what we
want to know is, what is the
probability under this
alternative distribution, that
we get a sample with a mean that
is lower than our critical
value? Because in that case, if,
if our mean is lower than the
critical value, we would fail to
reject the null hypothesis, even
though now we are looking at the
distribution where the null
hypothesis is objectively false,
because this distribution has a
mean of four and not of zero. So
given a mean of four, given that
the null hypothesis is false,
given that the mean is actually
four and not zero, what is the
probability of still only
getting a critical that value
here? Of 1.96? Okay, and we can
ask Excel for that. So I'm just
going to pull up Excel here. And
let's take a look. So what we
want here is we want to know,
what is the probability of
getting a value of 1.96 from a
normal distribution with a mean
of four and the standard
deviation of one. So I can write
here =NORM.DIST. And that
returns the normal distribution
for the specified mean, and
standard deviation. Okay, we
would like that. Okay. And then
then it says here, "x". So that
is the value that the or the
cutoff value that we want to get
the area to the left of for the
distribution. Okay. So 1.96,
comma, and then the mean of this
distribution -- 4 -- then the
standard deviation, we said 1,
and then the last one is, do you
want the cumulative
distribution? Or do you want
just the probability density
function? For our purposes, if
we want the area under the
curve, we always want
cumulative? The cumulative
distribution function, okay, we
always want true in this case.
Okay. So here, we are getting
.020675. Okay, so the value of
1.96 only cuts off about 2% of
the distribution given that the
null hypothesis is false. And
the alternative hypothesis that
the mean is actually 4 is true.
Okay, so we can get rid of
Excel. So yeah, so this tells us
again, this is just with
rounding. So it's .021, beta is
.021. So the power is one minus
point O two one. And that gives
us .9799 or rounded again, 98%.
Okay, so this is so I think,
maybe you've seen the principle,
but it is always nice to have a
visualisation for this And
someone called Kristoffer
Magnusson actually made a great
visual visualisation for this,
which I have the link to here.
So you can we can replicate our
analysis here. And then we can
try different values. So what
happens if we increase or
decrease sample size, we can
find out what sample size we
need for our power of .8. What
happens if we use reduce alpha t
.0025? So let's start with the
just replicating the analysis.
Okay, so here's that website.
And so here, this is the
visualisation. So you can see
that this, this makes things
possibly a lot clearer. So what
we just were trying to get was
power. Okay, so we said we
wanted an effect size of Cohen's
d of 1. So here we go. Oh, now
it's .97. Here's 1. Okay. We
said we had a sample size of 16.
And we wanted a significance
level of point oh, five, and we
would like to have a two tailed
right. So this is exactly what
we just calculated using Excel.
Only that here you have it now,
nicely visualised. Okay, so
here, and and you know, even you
can even hover over it over some
of the areas and it will tell
you, so, this, the dotted line
is the distribution given that
the null hypothesis is true.
Okay, so we're doing a two
tailed test. So it's centred on
zero. And we're doing a two
tailed test. So the rejection
regions are to the left, and to
the right. So this the area, the
red area, here is alpha, the two
areas together, okay, then,
here, we have the critical set
value, which we know. In our
case, which we know. In our
case, well, here, this is just
scaled a little bit differently,
because we don't have we have
this being a standard normal
distribution as well. So of the
distribution here, but
essentially, this is the
critical that value here. And it
cuts off exactly 2% of the
distribution given the
alternative hypothesis. And all
the other area on the
distribution here giving the
alternative hypothesis is power.
So the area this, this area, the
shaded in blue, and this
includes the this thing shaded
in red here, because this is
just in front of it, right. So
all of this (area under the
curve) until here, the critical
z-value, gives us the power.
Okay, so power, beta, and alpha.
And now we can see how things
change. So wow do things change,
if we reduce the sample size to,
let's say, eight. So you can
see, by reducing the sample
size, the distributions of the
mean of the sample mean get
wider, because remember you
there, we're dividing by the
square root of the sample size
to determine the standard error,
so, the greater the sample size,
the smaller the standard error,
and the narrower the
distributions are going to be.
So you can see now we have a lot
more overlap here, beta is a lot
greater alpha is still the same
at 5% Right, but now the price
of having an alpha of 5% is
having a beta of 19%. So by
reducing the number of
participants from 16 to eight,
our
beta goes up from 2% to 19%.
Okay, and we can also take a
look at what happens if you
change the significance level.
So if we go down to we can do
point two five, but we can do
point oh three, right. So what
happens so just to give you the
comparison, what happens is, if
you cut off a smaller part of
the My extreme parts only have
the distribution given that the
null hypothesis is true. That
means that the criterion moves
to the right, and also cuts off
a bigger part of the alternative
distribution. So that means beta
goes up. Right, so now we have
20%. Beta. If we reduce this to
point, a one, it goes even
further, and we have 40%. Beta,
right? While the type one error
is, of course, no one now,
because for the type one error,
we only have this tiny little
bit, you can't even hover over
that, (it is) so tiny, the
alpha. But the price of that was
a reduction in power. Okay. And
this is, of course, for a large
effect size. Let's, let's go
back to .05. And let's reset the
zoom so we can see all of the
distributions. So if we reduce
the effect size, that means,
let's see if you are prepared
for what's going to happen.
Think about what's going to
happen if I reduce the effect
size, what part of the plot is
going to change? Okay. All
right. So that's what's going to
change. Did you expect this that
the distributions would be
closer together? If so, well
done. So yeah, so now we have an
effect size of only half a
standard deviation. So Cohen's d
equals .5. And now, you can see
with this smaller effect size,
now the distributions overlap
quite a lot. And now actually,
we only have a power of 29%. How
could we get the power greater
again, well, we could increase
the sample size, let's say we go
to 30. Okay, and resetting the
zoom, so you can see better, so
that makes the distributions
narrower. And now, because they
are narrower, they overlap less.
And that also means that the
proportion cut off by the critic
criterion from the alternative
distribution is now lower again,
so 22%. Similarly, as you can,
you can use this to solve for
other things. So. So for
example, if we, so how many
participants do we need, in this
case, let's say we wanted a
power in this case of point
nine, five. So we can just
adjust the slider. And so we
would have the distributions,
they would have to be so narrow,
that only 5% of the area under
the alternative distribution is
smaller than the criteria. And
of course, 2.5% here and 2.5%
here, that's that is just the
alpha level, right? So so beta
here is controlled as 95% but it
means our sample size goes up
quite a bit. So 51.98. And since
we can't have .98 of a
participant in practice, it
would have to be 52 participants
right. And so, you can you can
just play with this a little bit
or you can you can see, I have a
sample size of 80 and I want I
want alpha of point o five and
power of point nine five, so
what is the smallest the
smallest effect size that I can
detect with this? And the answer
is .4, Cohen's d of .4. Okay. So
this is quite useful for you to
play with, and see how the, how
the different
how the different parameters
here of the of the test affect
the outcome given that the null
hypothesis is true, and given
that the null hypothesis is not.
Okay. And so, just to just to go
back to our example, from the
slides, so, if we have again, at
Cohen's d of one and we want a
power of .8, then we would need
-- let's just reset the zoom --
then we would need a sample size
of 7.85. So, 8, right, if that
is what we wanted. Okay, good.
So let's move on. So of course,
in reality, we don't have that
distribution. In reality, we
have to estimate the the
standard deviation of the
population and the standard
deviation of the sampling
distribution using the standard
deviation of the sample. And as
we said last week, This forces
us to use the t distribution.
Okay, so let's say, let's say we
still want to find a Cohen's d
of one. But now, we have two
groups in a t test. And we want
to calculate power, given our 16
participants, so eight per
group. And what the power is,
given Cohen's d of 1 and an
alpha level of .05, so let's go
to G*Power. Okay, so there it
is. And now we have a t-test,
again, so we want to get our two
independent means, okay. And now
the type of power analysis that
we want is compute achieved
power. So we want to see, what
power do we have, in this case
with a sample size of eight and
Group one, and eight in Group
two? Of course, we want two
tailed tests. And we want an
effect size of 1. So let's
calculate that. And you can see
we achieve a power of .461. So
46% power, or a beta of about
53? point, let's say 8%. Okay.
Okay. So what does a significant
result actually tell us? And,
and we got to that a little bit
when we talked about the
statements in the seminar
activity last week, so, but I
want to talk about it a little
bit more in terms of multiple
studies. And so what do we and
also in terms of, if you if you
actually got to in the seminar
activity if you got to the
exercise on sensitivity and
specificity? And so, in terms of
this of diagnosticity of a test,
right? So, what proportion of
significant p values is actually
due to a false positive? And
this is not. So again, if you if
you paid attention in the in the
seminar, for Question 1, you
will, you will probably be a
little bit more careful now. So,
what proportion of significant p
values is actually due to a
false positive? If you want to
say, .05, then, well, you are
right, given that the null
hypothesis is true, but we
actually don't know if the null
hypothesis is true or not.
Right. So, if, depending on
depending on whether the null
hypothesis -- if the hypothesis
is false, then well, then, of
course,
the significant p value is not
due to a false positive, right.
So, in reality, the significant
pair of p values that we get are
a mix of false positives and
true positives. Right. So, how
do we get the number of true
positives? And, again, if you
want to go back and look at
question three of the seminar
activity last week, to see the
parallels here, that would be a
very neat exercise for you to do
if you if you have the time. If
not, I don't blame you. Okay, so
let's make some assumptions.
Let's assume we have an alpha of
point oh five, we have a power
of point eight. And now we are
looking at 200 studies. And
again, going back to that
question 3 on "What's the
probability that I have COVID
given a positive test?" This is
very similar. What's the
probability that I have that I
have found an actual difference
in the world based on my
significant result, compared to
the probability that this is a
false positive? And I have
actually, and actually, there is
no true difference in the world.
Okay. So, if you remember, you
had to assume that you had to in
question three, you have to
assume something about the base
rate. So what percentage of
people with symptoms actually
have COVID. And like that, we
also have to assume similar
something about hypotheses. So
let's say, in psychology, 50%,
of all hypotheses that are
tested are actually true. And
then it's actually quite high.
So that would mean that people
are very good at making
hypotheses. But let's just say
it's 50%. So then, if we are
looking at 200 studies, at 200 t
tests, right, from from 200
different studies, then then 100
of them test a hypothesis that's
actually true. And 100 of them
test a hypothesis that's
actually false. And so let's
take, let's take a look at this,
then let's fill in this table.
So we know that we're using an
alpha level of point oh five,
right. So in this case, 95. So
if the null hypothesis is true,
we will not reject and correctly
not reject the null hypothesis
in 95, out of the 100 studies,
and we will incorrectly reject
the null hypothesis and five out
of those out of those 100
studies, right, and the
percentage that you have behind
there is what percentage this is
of the total of 200 studies.
Okay, so then, if the null
hypothesis is all is actually
false, and the alternative
hypothesis is true. So again, we
have 100 studies where that is
the case, then. So here, we have
to make another assumption, we
have to assume that our studies
have a power of point eight,
right? So in this case, which is
quite high. So in this case, we
reject the null, like, we
correctly reject the null
hypothesis for 80 out of the 100
studies, where the null
hypothesis is actually false,
and we fail to reject it
incorrectly. So committing a
type two error in 20, out of the
100 studies. Okay. So let's so
now let's take a look at at the
percentages here. And again, go
back to go back to Question
three, if you want to see the
parallel of this to the COVID
test,
because you're making the same
kind of table. Okay, so we have
85 significant tests. So
5+80=85. These are significance
test significant tests, where
the test rejects the null
hypothesis. Okay? So out of
those 85 significant tests, five
are false positives. So five
divided by 85 is 5.88%. And we
call this the false positive
rate. I mentioned this in the
seminar, as well in the well in
the seminar slides, at least if
you didn't get to the question.
And then 80 of the 85
significant tests are true
positives. So that's one minus
basically -- well, it's in terms
of percentages 100 minus the
false positive rate. So this is
the positive predictive value.
And these team terms were coined
by John Ioannides this in a
research paper that got a lot of
attention, you can click on this
and and read it. Unfortunately,
John iron ideas has, well, he
has maybe well, he's he's sort
of gone out of his area of
expertise recently with with
COVID. So If you're interested
in that, look it up it has sort
of damaged the the image that a
lot of people had of him.
Similar to quite similar to
Daryl -- to what happened with
Daryl Bem. Right. So So I guess
everyone has their particular
area where they may be, well,
where they may be a little bit
outside of what, what would
possibly be a reasonable
position. But anyway, in this
paper was very well received.
And it was actually about the
false positive rate in medicine.
And in medicine, the situation
is actually a bit better than in
psychology because at least
there you have clinical studies
that are pre registered, and
very carefully controlled double
blind studies, which in
psychology, we tend to do very
little of those kind of double
blind studies where the
experimenter also doesn't know
which group the participant is
in, or what condition the the
participant is working. But
still, his conclusion was in
their paper, that the state of
testing in medicine was quite
worrying with a high false
positive rate, and a much lower
positive predictive value than
you would want in something as
important as clinical testing.
So why is this a problem, so
maybe you didn't find this
results in the table to be
looking so bad, I mean, false
positive rate of 5.88. That's
not, that's not terrible. But
that is also assuming that
making some assumptions that
maybe aren't that that
realistic. So there is a an
interactive visualisation of the
false positive rate by Felix
Schnbrodt, which I have the
link of here. So first, we are
going to take a look at the
situation that I put in the
table as an example. And then we
can explore other situations.
And there's also an option
called the percentage of
phacked studies. And I will
talk about that in a second. So
those are studies where people,
for example, do things like
multiple testing, or without
correcting for it, and that just
turns values that should be, or
tests that should be
non-significant into significant
tests, because of problems with
just applying the null
hypothesis significance testing
method, and a nice and short way
of calling this is p-hacking. So
hacking in the sense of, I am
sort of messing with the system
of null hypothesis significance
testing, until I get what I
want, which could be one one
definition of hacking in
software as well.
Okay, so let's take a look at
the visualisation now. And as
you can see, this is called when
does a significant p-value
indicate a true effect,
understanding the positive
predictive value of a p-value?
Okay, so on the left side, you
have the parameters of the
simulation. So you've got
percent of a-priori true
hypotheses. So this, this means
how many prior how many
hypotheses that we make, for
example, in psychology are
actually true. Before we do
that, so (how many) are actually
true and how many are false;
here it's set to 30. Let's,
let's assume the same thing as
in the table and set it to 50.
Then alpha level .05, we'll
leave that do we want to specify
power directly or indirectly
through sample size and effect
size, we can specify it here
directly, we can set it to 2.8.
The number of p hat studies, we
will leave that at zero for now.
Okay? So and you can see we've
replicated the results from the
table. Right? So 40% true
positives 10% false negatives
47.5%, true negatives 2.5% false
positives. So that gives us a
positive predict. The value of
95.1% and a false discovery rate
of 5.9%. So, yeah, just what,
what we found, and in this
visualisation, so each point is
one study here. So the false
positives are in red, the true
negatives are in yellow, the
true positives are in green, and
the false negatives are in blue.
Okay, so here you can see, in
this case, with 80%, power, 50%
true hypotheses, alpha of .05,
or 5%. Most of the studies are
either true negatives or true
positives. There are some false
negatives. So remember, power is
just .8, so 20%, false
negatives, and a small number of
false positives, because alpha
is at .05, so 5%. If we only
consider the significant
findings, the ratio of true to
false positives looks like this:
Right? So now we're taking all
the negatives out the true and
the false negatives, and just
consider the relationship
between true and false
positives. And there are many
more false positives, of course,
than true positives. All right.
I think I just reset, just reset
the page, but not a problem.
Okay, here we got it. Again, it
just went back to the default
values. Okay, so now, now we can
try this out a little bit. So,
so yeah, so if we, let's say we
still have power of point eight,
but now only 30% of a-priori
true hypotheses. So then most
hypotheses are false here, so
you got more yellow and red. And
because you've got more, because
you've got more positive, more,
more false hypothesis. In
general, of course, you also
have more false positives, you
have fewer false negatives,
because you have fewer negative
few negatives. And, of course,
you have also fewer true
positives. So with this, now,
our our false positives have
gone up a little and our true
positives have gone down. So now
12% of all claimed findings are
actually false positives. And we
can keep doing this. We can also
say, Well, now let's set it to
50% power, which is more of
maybe what happens in
psychology. So that means we
have more false negatives, now,
we have even fewer true
positives. So that means that
now we have a false discovery
rate of 18.9%. Okay, so now,
adding to this p-hacked studies,
let's say, let's say 10% of
studies contain questionable
research practices. So now, now
10% of the yellow points have
turned red. So they have become
false positives, instead of true
negatives. So now we have
we have many more false
positives, and the number of
true positives hasn't actually
changed. So now, we are at a
scenario where failure where
38.1% of claim findings are
false. And so so out of out of
every 10 papers that you're
looking at, in there now for our
faults. And so in the paper by
Ioannides you've got different
scenarios, so like, registered
clinical trial, with little
bias. So there you would have
15% of claim findings that are
false. You could also switch it
to for example, a poorly
performed clinical trial where
the assumption is that 80% of
all results are p-hacked. So
then there we would have 82% of
claim findings that are false.
In psychology, we would probably
have something hopefully, like,
an adequately powered,
exploratory study. So well,
exploratory means most of your
hypotheses are false. Because
you're just exploratory in this
case means you're just trying
different things, see what
sticks. It's adequately powered,
it has point eight. But we still
have p-hacked study. So even if
we go with p-hacked studies to
zero -- oh no, it's 100 now --
now, let's go to set p-hacked
studies to zero, even then, in
this case, we have only, we have
still 38.7% of claimed findings
false. And if we set the number
of px studies to 30, then again,
we have 80% of claimed findings
that are false. So it is really,
it is a bit of a scary
visualisation here to see,
depending on how optimistic or
pessimistic we are about the
percentage of true hypotheses,
for example, and the level of
pee hacking. Maybe most of the
research that's published is
actually false. Right? Now,
people are probably going to
have questions about the
percentage of true hypotheses.
And you're right, that this is
something that is not completely
clear how you arrive at this
value. I mean, the replication
project in psychology had was
able to replicate maybe between
30 and 40%, I think it was
something like 38% or 37%, of
all of the studies. So if we
have that, and we have a power
of point eight, and we are very
hopeful that only problems only
exist in 10% of all studies,
then well, then maybe only 23%
of claim findings are false. But
that is still more than one in
five, right? So it is, so it is
a problem. And I hope this
visualisation helps you a little
bit in in seeing the scale of
magnitude of the problem. Okay,
so, so going back to our
presentation, just to to address
the question of how does
p-hacking happen? We have
already said multiple
comparisons without controlling.
In general, when you perform an
experiment, or any kind of
study, you have what's called
experiment the degrees of
freedom. And if you watched the
video by Andrew Gelman that I
had in the lecture one
materials, then he talks about
the multiverse of possible data
analyses. So there are a lot and
there are lots of things that
you can do with your data. So do
you aggregate the data in a
particular way? Do you add a
control variable? Do you enter
something as a continuous
variable or as a discrete
variable? So do you do things
like a median split, to split a
continuous variable into high
and low, and all of those things
affect the outcome of the data
analysis, and all of these can
lead to false positives. If you
if you do things like, Well, if
you if you try different ones,
different versions of analysing
the data, and then just stick
with the one that has,
that manages to reject the null
hypothesis. And if you listen to
this now, as someone who has
probably never done a study
before sat, but some of you will
do a study, or maybe you've done
your psychology project, but
possibly that was not
significant. Anyway. So you
might not have had this problem.
But it's very easy to get into
this kind of mindset where you
say, "Well, I, I am quite sure
that my hypothesis is actually
true. My alternative, my
experimental hypothesis is
actually true. And I just need
to find so if I if I don't find
it, if I don't find it in my
analysis, then I must be doing
something wrong. So I need to
change my analysis, sort of
learn from my data and tweak my
analysis until I find what I
think must be there". And this
is a very dangerous attitude,
but it is also very
understandable in people who are
doing experiments, especially
for the first time. And
unfortunately, I think in some
people, it just this attitude
just persists because no one
ever tells them any better. They
don't, they just don't know
better. They think that their
analysis choices are justified
by the outcomes that they're
finding an effect that they
think is there anyway. Because
that's what they believe, like
power posing it. If you think
about it enough, I think if you
work about it, if you work on
it, for long enough, you really
develop a very strong conviction
that it is real, that it is a
true effect. And then you will,
and then from there, too, I'm
not saying that Amy Cuddy did
this. I don't know, I haven't
looked at it in that much
detail, right?. I've been I've
read the analysis that other
people had of their work. But
then it is very easy to get into
the mindset of saying, if I'm
not finding the effect, I'm
doing something wrong, so I'm
trying different things until I
get it right, which is finding
the effect. And that is a
problem, of course. Another
thing is HARKing hypothesising,
after the results are no. So
that would be something like
saying, Okay, I am studying
depression, I am really
interested in,
in the mood variable. But I
don't find anything there. So
now I'm thinking, "Hmm, what,
what, what about sleep quality?"
And maybe I go back to my
participants, and I have them do
a sleep quality, sleep quality
measure. And then I test that,
and, and, oh, is that suddenly
significant? Or maybe if it's
not significant, maybe I go back
and try another measure, maybe I
try to split by, by gender. Or
maybe I tried to split by
socioeconomic status and things
like that, right. And all of
these, so all of these
hypotheses, I'm coming up with
hypotheses based on my data, and
not based on the theory. And
that is also very dangerous.
Because if you use the same
data, to confirm your hypotheses
that you've used to come up with
it, that is not a proper test
that because then you are going
to find, you're going to find
your effect, because you're
studying it on the very same
data where you have observed the
effect, right? The point is, or
the the idea is that you do
exploration, maybe on one
datasets, you just look at
everything that's in one data
set and say, Oh, look, there's a
difference in gender. And then
you try to replicate it in a
different data set. So (in terms
of) exploratory and confirmatory
research, HARKing, is mixing,
exploratory and confirmatory
research. Okay, then we already
talked about multiple
comparisons without controlling
for them. And then, of course,
you could also have assumption
violations so that you just do
the test, you just do a test
that is not appropriate for your
data. But really, that is
usually fairly well policed by
peer review. First of all,
because it's an easy objective
thing to criticise your study
on. And secondly, the effects of
assumption violations. And we'll
talk about this later in, in
this unit. But the effects of
assumption violations compared
to the effects of experimental
degree of freedom, harking,
multiple comparisons, just
p-hacking in general, are so
tiny, that actually, it's hard
for me to think of a study that
had a false positive due to an
assumption violation, but plenty
of studies that had false
positives due to HARKing,
experimenter  degrees of
freedom, things like that, that
did not replicate because of
that, not because you did the
wrong analysis on analysis, that
wasn't appropriate. And the
funny thing is that in
undergraduate psychology
statistics, I hope it's
changing, but but at least it
used to be that you would spend
endless time on assumption
violations and just ignoring
p-hacking experimented degrees
of freedom. Maybe you talked a
little bit about Bonferroni
corrections, but that was pretty
much it. Right? So you spend a
lot of time on on small on a
small issue. assumption
violations. We'll talk about it
later. How, for example, with
tests like ANOVA, they are so
robust that many assumption
violations don't really change
the outcome. So you spend a lot
of time on those, but you spend
very little time on the actual
problems, which is, which are
p-hacking, underpowered studies?
Bad hypothesising, those other
kinds of things that that cause
real problems in psychology and
with replicability. So again,
we've already we've played
through this on the
visualisation, so I'm not going
to go back to that now. But if
we put in 40% of hypotheses that
are true, so so this is
generous, right? average power
is point five, it might be lower
10% of studies or P hacked, then
we get a false discovery rate of
28.3. And so between 1 in 4 and
1 in 3 psychology studies with
significant results are actually
false. And if you make more
pessimistic assumptions, then
you would get a worse picture
and now relevant for your
assignment, for the coursework.
For the essay, try playing with
the alpha slider, try seeing
what happens when you go from
point .05 to .005, and I'm not
going to tell you what happens,
you have to try it and then and
then see if you can use that for
your essay.
Okay. So then finally, so I in
the past lectures and workshops
and seminars, I have often
hinted at the fact that Fisher
caused the problem with his
approach to the interpretation
of p values. So Fisher's
conception of probability was
somewhere between subjective and
objective. And he did not like
like, name and Pearson's
approach. In fact, they hated
each other so much that Neyman
and Pearson moved from the UK to
the US, just to be far away from
Fisher. Well, I'm sure there
were other reasons, but I think
it was a major reason, they
really didn't like each other.
So in Fishers opinion, a p value
of.01 provides more evidence
against the null hypothesis,
then a p value of .05. And
because Fisher was very
influential, people started
imitating this. The problem is
that Fisher never claimed to be
doing all hypothesis
significance testing. And the
problem is that people started
conflating the strict null
hypothesis significance testing
that Neyman and Pearson proposed
with Fisher's approach to using
p values as an an indication of
evidence or effect size of
strength of evidence. And the
two things just don't go
together, you can either do one
or the other. But people started
pretending that they're doing
null hypothesis significance
testing, but mixing it up with,
with ideas from Fischer, and
that, that led to the
problematic situation where we,
that we are in now. So the
rejection rules are strict for a
reason. If you don't do non
hypothesis significance testing
in a principled way, you are not
going to get the outcome that
you think you're getting, but
you are then communicating it as
if you had been following the
rules. So in general, using p
values as measures of evidence
is a bad idea. And we have
better ways of doing that, using
Bayesian methods. I will see
that in the next lecture. So
finally, to summarise our
criticism of null hypothesis
significance testing: First, it
is inflexible and offers only
black and white decisions. And
it offers only two decisions.
Remember that, right? Only
reject a null hypothesis, or
fail to reject the null
hypothesis. There's nothing else
there's no accepting the null
hypothesis. There is no
accepting the alternative
rejecting the alternative
hypothesis. No, there's only
rejecting the null hypothesis or
not rejecting the null
hypothesis. There is nothing
else. Okay? And that can be a
problem. For example, what if
you're actually interested in
the null hypothesis? What if you
want to show that there is no
difference? No hypothesis
significance testing does not
really have a mechanism for
that. And people have sort of
tried to do it by doing a test
with very high power, and then
saying, Okay, I had extremely
high power. So if an effect was
there, I should have found it.
But instead I failed to reject
the null hypothesis. And, well,
they've that has sort of worked
in the past, but it's not great.
Because you're essentially using
the logic of null hypothesis
significance testing and turning
it around. Also, the whole
concept of significance. So
--and this is something where
people intuitively see that
Fisher was of course, right,
right, that that if you get a
very low p value, there is
something different about a very
low p value, compared to a p
value that's close to .05.
Right? There is something
different about that. But the
problem is, in non partisan
significance testing, you're
supposed to completely ignore
that. Because otherwise, your
strict testing rules go out of
the window. Okay? So so you can
also understand why people why
people would do things like say,
"Oh, this is marginally
significant, or this is very
significant," right? highly
significant. If you're using
null hypothesis significance
testing, do not use terms like
highly significant, or almost
significant, or marginally
significant or close to
significance. There is no such
such thing. They're significant,
and there is not significant.
That's all there is. But of
course, people feel that, that
doesn't quite describe what
they're seeing. And that is the
problem. So you can also say
that, well, the focus on null
hypotheses limits the amount of
thinking that researchers do
about the alternative
hypotheses. So usually, I mean,
you have to, you only have to
specify the alternative
hypothesis a little bit if you
want to, if you want to find out
power, because for that you need
you need some kind of idea about
what your alternative hypothesis
is, if you haven't cared about
power, then you don't need to
think about what the alternative
hypothesis is at all. So that,
and as a result, you're usually
what you see the alternative
hypotheses that you see, are
very, very vague. Most
hypotheses are also just not
realistic. It's very unlikely in
nature for anything to be
exactly zero. It may the true
difference may well be very
close to zero. But it's unlikely
to have an exact that things are
exactly exactly exactly the
same. So that's, that is an
issue. So in a way, the
knowledge hypothesis is this
kind of straw man, that doesn't
really that isn't even
realistic. So then, of course,
we have the familywise error
rate. So the problem with this
is, what is the reference class
here. And the problem is that it
depends on what you were
planning on doing. So if you
have a t-test with p = .04, if
this is the only t-test you plan
on doing, it is significant. The
exact same result, if you're
planning on doing a second
t-test, is no longer
significant. So unless you write
down very clearly, what you are
planning on doing, it's very
easy to just trick yourself into
thinking, "Oh, I wasn't actually
going to run that second
t-test," even though you would
have absolutely run the second T
test if the first one hadn't
resulted significant. Right. So
and with stopping rules, it gets
even more extreme. So if you
have one scientist, that tests
30 participants and another
scientist that tests 30
participants. If the first
scientist, checked the data at
15 participants would have
stopped, but didn't. And the
second part, the second
scientist didn't check the data,
then they could have the exact
exact same means the exact same
results, but one would have a
significant result. So the one
who didn't stop and peek, and
the other one would have a
nonsignificant result. And that
is a problem. That doesn't
really make a lot of sense. So
in the next lecture, we will
talk about an alternative to
null hypothesis significance
testing, just Bayesian
statistics and maybe you We'll
find that these are a lot more
intuitive compared to what we've
done now. But it is of course
important to talk about another
hypothesis significance testing,
because that's what almost
everyone is doing today.
Bayesian statistics is sort of
gaining, but there's still a
long way to go. Still most
studies report p values. Okay.
And that is it for this week.
Thank you very much for listening.